这里是通往一处自然界奇观的入口
This is the entrance to one of the greatest of natural wonders…
这就是位于越南的韩松洞
Hang Son Doong in Vietnam.
据称 这里是全世界最大的洞穴
It's thought to be the largest cave on Earth.
在地下200多米的深邃洞穴中
Here, two hundred metres underground,
每年只有几个星期
for just a few weeks a year,
阳光可以透过顶部的一个小洞照进洞内
sunbeams cast light through a hole in the cave's roof.
而这些光亮
That is just enough light,
已经足够植物生长
to enable plants to grow.
当你再向深处探索 又会陷入黑暗之中
But travel deeper and darkness returns,
这是生命很难跨越的极限之地
and you reach the limit of where life can exist.
我们人类通常很难涉足
These most extreme places on our planet
这些地球上的极端环境
are often hard for us to reach.
事实上 韩松洞在不久前才被发现
Indeed, this cave was only recently discovered.
这里有很多令人叹为观止的奇特景象
And it contains many surprises.
比如洞内的穴珠
Cave pearls -
它们最初只是细小的沙粒
once tiny sand grains,
但如今已有网球大小
now spheres the size of tennis balls.
还有巨大的石笋
And giant stalagmites,
由成千上万年来的
formed over centuries
上千亿颗水滴滴落沉积而成
by billions of individual drops of water.
地下河在石灰岩体中
Underground rivers
穿凿出这条巨大的洞穴通道
have carved this great passage through the limestone.
韩松洞全长超过8公里
Over five miles long
内部空间巨大 有些地方甚至可以
and wide enough in places,
容纳一架巨型喷气式飞机
to accommodate a jumbo jet.
然而在洞穴尽头的洞室
And it is here - in the cave's furthest chamber -
依然能发现生命的迹象
that life can be found.
韩松洞中半透明的洞穴盲鱼
Translucent cave fish…
和沼虾
and shrimps -
这些物种在数千年的时间里与世隔绝
isolated for millennia -
靠地表丛林中渗透下来的少量营养物质
feeding on little more than the nutrients
顽强生存下来
from the jungle above.
洞穴盲鱼完全看不见东西
The fish are completely blind,
只能靠触觉探知四周
and find their way about by touch alone.
韩松洞的地下世界
These underground worlds
是生命存活的极端之境
are at the very limit of where life can exist…
而地面之上的极端环境
But above ground, our planet's most extreme conditions
大多出现在极地地区
are found at the poles.
北极地区冬季的气温
Here in the north, winter temperatures
有时可以降到零下50摄氏度
can drop to minus fifty degrees Celsius.
一年中有4个月的时间
For four months of the year,
这里几乎看不到一丝阳光
there is barely a glimmer of sunlight.
可即便在这样的地方
But here too,
生命依然有其生存之道
life finds a way to survive.
这是一群北极狼
A pack of Arctic wolves.
浓密的皮毛
Their dense fur
保护它们度过了长达数月的严寒
has protected them through months of bitter cold.
此刻 阳光终于重回大地
But now the sun is returning
这里是埃尔斯米尔岛
This is Ellesmere Island.
北极狼群必须趁着短暂夏季的到来
The short summer gives the wolves a chance
增强体力
to rebuild their strength.
可北极地区的生活
But here in the Arctic,
从来都不容易
life is never easy.
这个狼群的首领
This pack
是一只经验丰富的雌性北极狼
is led by an experienced female.
如果它不能带领狼群找到食物
If she can't lead them to food,
那么同伴们就可能熬不过下一个寒冬
the coming winter could be their last.
捕食对象散布在辽阔的冰原上
Prey is spread over such a vast area,
狼群必须不停地奔袭
that they must be constantly on the move…
展开搜寻
in search of it.
但是发现目标仅仅是捕猎行动的开始
But finding prey is only the beginning.
这里有一群麝牛
Musk-oxen.
它们的体形几乎是北极狼的5倍
They are five times the size of a wolf.
北极狼与麝牛之间的冲突由来已久
The conflict between wolf and oxen is an ancient one,
可以追溯到冰川时期
and has been waged since the Ice Age.
它们双方都很清楚彼此的攻防策略
Each side knows the other's tactics.
北极狼会尝试孤立体弱或年幼的麝牛
The wolves try to isolate the weak or the young.
一头麝牛幼崽跌绊了一下
A calf stumbles -
北极狼首领立刻逼近
and the pack leader immediately closes in.
此时麝牛群重新聚拢队伍
But the herd regroups,
亮出牛角准备迎敌
horns at the ready.
双方陷入僵局
Stalemate…
但这里不宜久留
but it can only be brief.
这一次
This time,
麝牛群跑到了地势更高的山坡上
the herd race to higher ground.
当它们来到山脊上
As they reach the top of the ridge,
雄性麝牛转身做好防御准备
the males turn to defend themselves.
双方又陷入了对峙局面
Stalemate - again.
每一次捕猎行动的失败
Every unsuccessful hunt
都会削弱北极狼群的实力
leaves the pack weakened.
这或许是唾手可得的美餐
This could be an easier meal.
可情况不太对
But something is not right...
这头麝牛是病死的
this musk ox has died from a disease.
随着北极地区的气候变暖
Outbreaks like this are becoming increasingly common
这样的疫情变得越来越常见
as the climate warms across the Arctic.
狼群虽然很饿
Despite their hunger,
但它们还是决定放弃这具尸体
the pack don't eat this carcass.
又一群麝牛出现了
Another herd…
这是北极狼群的第二次机会
another chance for the pack.
这一次 北极狼冲散了麝牛群
This time, the wolves manage to split the herd,
这或许能提高它们捕获猎物的概率
that may improve their chances.
雌性北极狼首领
The lead female
极力避免麝牛又一次跑上山脊
makes sure that the oxen do not reach the ridge again.
又少了一位防御者
With one less defender,
麝牛群中的幼崽会更加无助
the calf is more vulnerable.
它们终于可以饱餐一顿了
A much-needed meal.
北极狼群必须在夏季结束之前
The wolves must continue to make the most
抓紧时间捕猎
of the remaining weeks of summer.
这样 当北极的寒冬再次到来时
So, when winter returns,
它们才足以熬过
they are ready to endure
这段地球上
some of the harshest conditions
条件最为严酷的时期
that exist on Planet Earth.
在极地地区之外
Such inhospitable extremes
也存在与之类似的极端环境
are not only found at the Poles.
随着海拔的升高
As altitude increases,
高山上的气温会急剧下降
temperatures fall.
这里的动物
Here too,
也要学会充分利用季节变化带来的机遇
animals must make the most of the seasonal change.
尤其是在准备交配的季节
Particularly if you are ready to mate.
在法国的阿尔卑斯山上
A male common frog
一只雄性欧洲林蛙出现了
in the French Alps.
它整个冬天都在冰层之下冬眠
He has spent all winter hibernating under the ice.
现在是时候苏醒了
But now it's time to wake up.
欧洲林蛙是变温动物
Being cold-blooded,
需要靠阳光来提高体温
he needs the sun to warm his body.
但如果保持不动
But once it sets in a few hours time,
它几小时内就会被冻死
he could freeze to death.
所以它必须抓紧时间寻找伴侣
So finding a mate is urgent.
天气很好
The weather is good
它开始在雪地上滑行加速
and he starts to sledge.
而这里不只是它在孤勇奋战
But this is not a one-frog race.
几十只欧洲林蛙涌向一处可供交配的池塘
Dozens are rushing to the breeding pool.
这么多欧洲林蛙出现在坡道上
This many frogs out on the slopes
自然会惹来关注
doesn't go unnoticed.
小心 别掉进洞里
You can't afford any slips.
似乎一切还算顺利
It was all going so well.
成功到达
Made it.
但是所有的雌性已经找到了伴侣
But all the females have already got partners.
只剩一个办法了
There's only one thing for it…
摔跤大战
wrestling.
这次没能如愿
Not this time.
又一只欧洲林蛙姗姗来迟
Another latecomer,
是一只雌性
a female.
它能中意自己吗
Could she be the one?
有些时候 来得早不如来得巧
Sometimes being late can pay off.
雄性欧洲林蛙付出了很多努力
After all his efforts,
它绝不会轻易放过
the male is not going to let this chance
这次难得的机会
slip through his fingers.
这是非洲北部
This is the cedar forest
阿特拉斯山脉的雪松林
of the Atlas Mountains in North Africa.
这些无尾猕猴（又名巴巴里猕猴）
These Barbary macaques
悠闲度过了食物丰富的夏季
enjoyed a summer of plenty,
现在要付出代价了
but now they are paying the price.
冬季要面临刺骨的严寒
Winter here can be brutal.
在一些年份
In some years,
半数以上的无尾猕猴会失去生命
over half the group perish.
不过 在无尾猕猴的族群中
But in this macaque society,
与同伴关系越紧密
the more social the monkey,
生存下去的机会就越大
the more likely it is to survive -
相互依偎 抱团取暖
keeping warm by huddling
是它们重要的生存策略
can make all the difference.
可它们不能整天待在一起
But they can't huddle all day.
有些时候必须分开去觅食
They must, eventually, break apart to feed.
它们分散到各处寻找食物
They spread out, searching for food.
一旦入夜
But each night,
族群又会回到雪松树上抱成一团
the group return to huddle in the cedar trees.
任何一个成员都不希望被排除在外
No one wants to be left out -
尤其是柔弱的幼崽
especially the infants.
可这只无尾猕猴幼崽却和同伴走散了
This baby - somehow - has got separated.
它必须尽快回到伙伴温暖的怀抱中
He must get back to the life-saving warmth of the huddle - and soon.
可落单的幼崽却遇到了阻碍
But there is an obstacle.
一只脾气暴躁的雄性无尾猕猴
A grumpy male
冷漠地推开了它
is giving the baby a rather cold shoulder.
或许它应该轻轻地靠近对方
Maybe a more subtle approach…
雄性无尾猕猴决定独自离开
the male decides to leave.
最终
At last,
落单的幼崽找到一个温暖的怀抱
an enthusiastic reception.
可是离开的雄性无尾猕猴就没那么幸运了
The male has had less luck.
这一夜恐怕会非常难熬
It could be a long night.
拥抱对人类而言或许只是一种情感表达
Huddling might seem a simple expression of affection,
但对这些无尾猕猴来说
but among these macaques,
却是重要的生存方式
it's essential for survival.
而且不只是这里
And not just here.
在8000多公里外的墨西哥丛林中
Five thousand miles away in the forests of Mexico -
数百万只黑脉金斑蝶
Monarch butterflies - in millions -
也在相互依偎求生
also huddle for survival.
它们为了躲避北美大陆即将到来的冬季
All of them have travelled across North America
不远千里来到这里
to escape the winter that is coming there.
不过在这片海拔3000多米的森林中
This forest, at an altitude of three thousand meters,
也存在一些挑战
might seem to offer little comfort -
有时气温也会降到冰点以下
for temperatures here can drop below freezing -
同样有可能造成黑脉金斑蝶死亡
and that could kill butterflies.
好在这里的树冠
But in fact, a thin layer of warm air,
可以锁住一层薄薄的暖空气
trapped by the tree canopy,
只要树林环境不受打扰
protects them and will do so throughout the winter,
就可以保护它们安然度过冬季
provided that the forest remains undisturbed.
但不可预测的极端天气
Unpredictable extremes of weather, however,
有时会破坏这种微妙的平衡
can disrupt this delicate balance.
大风会把冷空气带入丛林深处
Strong winds can push deep into the forest -
造成气温骤降
chilling the air.
成千上万的黑脉金斑蝶
Hundreds of thousands of butterflies
被狂风吹落树梢
may be blown from the branches.
在一些年份里
In some years,
75%的黑脉金斑蝶
storms kill seventy-five per cent
都会因风暴而丢掉性命
of hibernating monarchs.
这一只侥幸逃过一劫
This one has survived…
但它不能待在地面上
but on the ground,
夜间的霜冻对它同样致命
and night-time frosts are fatal.
要想活命 就必须离开这里
It can't stay here - and live.
气温太低 它根本飞不起来
It is too cold to fly,
可现在必须要回到树枝上
but it must get back into the trees branches somehow.
于是它开始奋力攀爬
So it starts to climb.
这就像人类徒手爬上摩天大楼
It's the equivalent of a human climbing up a skyscraper.
终于安全了
Safety at last.
春回大地
As spring returns,
黑脉金斑蝶从漫长的冬眠中醒来
the monarchs wake from their long slumber.
它们即将开始自然界一项了不起的壮举
And now starts one of Earth's greatest natural spectacles.
然而 这场宏大的复苏盛景
But this mass-awakening
同样面临着巨大的威胁
is under threat.
气候变暖造成极端天气频发
The changing climate is creating more extreme weather
风暴的出现越来越频繁
and storms are becoming more frequent.
但至少到目前为止
But for now,
这场自然界的奇迹还在继续
this miracle of nature continues.
火灾
Fire -
它难以预测 破坏力极强
unpredictable and destructive.
这里是南非的凡波斯生态区
This is South Africa's fynbos…
是地球上植物种类最丰富的地区
botanically one of the most diverse habitats on Earth,
拥有8000多种不同的植物
with over eight thousand different plant species.
可每过20年左右
Yet every two decades,
这里就会发生一场大火将植被化为灰烬
fire reduces the vegetation to ashes.
这种火灾似乎破坏力极强
This may seem catastrophic…
可过不了几天
but just days later,
植物又会破土而出
plants burst into life
这里的景观又会焕然一新
and transform the landscape.
植物的种子和球茎
Seeds and bulbs
都在等待大火带来的机会
have been waiting for this event.
9000万年来 有些植物浴火而生
Ninety million years of evolution alongside fire
已经完全适应了火焰的洗礼
has made some plants so closely adapted
甚至没有浓烟就无法生根发芽
that they can't germinate without the presence of smoke.
引人关注的是
Remarkably,
地球上大约50%的陆地栖息地
around fifty per cent of Planet Earth's terrestrial habitats
都要靠大火来保持健康的环境条件
depend on fire to remain healthy.
澳大利亚北部的热带草原
In northern Australia,
也需要季节性大火来保持空间的开阔
these savannahs need seasonal fires to keep them open
阻止附近的森林扩张
and prevent the spread of the nearby forest.
一种色彩鲜艳的动物
And they are a vital habitat
就生活在这片开阔的草原上
for this colourful resident.
它们就是稀有动物金肩鹦鹉
The rare golden-shouldered parrot.
这只雄性金肩鹦鹉和它的伴侣
He and his lifelong partner
需要在草原上
rely on grassland
寻找食物和筑巢
for both food, and a nest site.
像往常一样
As usual,
它们会在白蚁丘中挖洞产卵
they've laid their eggs in a hole in a termite mound
现在已孵化出了4只雏鸟
and now there are four chicks.
白蚁丘厚厚的泥质外壳
The thick mud walls
不仅可以保护雏鸟免受捕食动物的伤害
don't only protect chicks from predators
还能帮它们躲避烈日的炙烤
but insulate them from the heat of the scorching sun.
这几只雏鸟很快就会羽翼丰满
With fledging just days away,
它们的父母都在加班加点地劳作
the parents are working overtime.
它们每天都能采集数千粒种子
They collect thousands of seeds, every day.
但现在 它们也遇到了难题
But they have a problem.
火灾发生的时间越来越不规律
The fire season is becoming more irregular.
如果雏鸟还没有学会飞行
If they are not ready to fly,
必然无处可逃
chicks have no escape.
不过 选择在白蚁丘中筑巢
But choosing to nest in a termite mound
还有个意外的好处
has a surprise benefit -
它们的巢穴可以防火
their home is fireproof.
白蚁丘的外壳就像混凝土墙
Concrete-like walls
雏鸟躲在里面可以安全避开外面的大火
keep chicks safe from the flames outside.
过火的草地变得焦黑
The seeds of fire grass
金肩鹦鹉更容易找到草种
are now easier for the parrots to find on the blackened earth -
这是它们最喜欢的食物
and they are the parrots' favorite food.
所以对成年金肩鹦鹉
So for both adults
和羽翼未丰的雏鸟而言
and their fledgling chicks,
大火也是它们生存的必要条件
fires are essential for survival.
不过 它们居住的这片草原
But their grassland home
面积正在逐渐缩小
is shrinking,
目前全球的金肩鹦鹉数量
and only about a thousand of these lovely parrots
仅剩1000只左右
still survive.
当地人积极管理草原火情
It's through the active management of fire by humans,
帮它们保住了这片仅存的小天地
that their world now exists at all.
人类活动对全球各地的自然栖息地
Humans are affecting habitats across Planet Earth -
都产生了显著影响
for wildlife, all too often,
而且往往会给野生动物带来灾难性的后果
the consequences have been disastrous.
非洲象是承受能力最强的动物之一
Elephants are among the most tolerant of animals.
它们的寿命很长
They are very long-lived
生存知识可以世代相传
and knowledge passed between generations
帮助后代在面临极端环境威胁时
enables them to find food and little-used sources of water
找到食物和稀有的水源
in times of great environmental stress.
但是现在 连非洲象的生存策略
But even among elephants, survival strategies
也显得有些无能为力
are now beginning to fail.
在肯尼亚的安波塞利国家公园
In Amboseli, Kenya,
多年的极端天气
years of extreme weather
和当地牧民的过度放牧
combined with overgrazing by domestic cattle
几乎将这片草原变成了荒漠
are turning these grasslands to dust.
这头雌性非洲象首领已经40多岁了
This matriarch is over forty years old -
它经历过非洲东部最严重的干旱
and she has already survived
并顺利渡过了难关
some of East Africa's worst droughts.
可今年
But this year,
植物数量急剧减少
food is in extremely short supply -
它和幼崽很难找到足够的食物
and her family are struggling to find enough.
它最年幼的一头雄性幼崽
Her youngest son
已经出现营养不良
is malnourished
身体越来越虚弱
and weak.
它有些跟不上妈妈和哥哥的脚步了
And is lagging behind his mother and brother.
雌性非洲象带着幼崽们
She leads them
来到自己熟悉的一片金合欢树林
to a pocket of acacia forest that she knows well.
可断裂的树枝和倾倒的树木说明
But broken branches and fallen trees show that
别的大象已经来过这个地方
other elephants have already been here.
这里没剩下多少能吃的东西了
There is very little left worth eating.
没有食物
Without food,
雌性非洲象无法分泌出足够的奶水
his mother cannot produce enough milk.
它别无选择
She has no choice…
只能离开越来越虚弱的幼崽
but to leave her weakening calf -
到别处去寻找食物
and try to find food elsewhere.
于是雌性非洲象
So she
和它年长的雄性幼崽出发了
and her elder son head off…
虚弱的幼崽被丢下了
without him.
它只能期盼妈妈和哥哥赶快回来
He can only hope for their return.
可是它的时间已经不多了
But for him, time has run out.
雌性非洲象和其它同伴已经无计可施
There is nothing his mother or anybody,
根本救不了它
could have done to save him.
对雌性非洲象来说 只要年长的幼崽还活着
With her elder son still alive,
它的族群就有希望
there is hope for her family.
但它们必须尽快适应环境的变化
But only if they can adapt quickly.
有些族群展现出强大的韧性
Some families are proving to be resilient -
它们会离开安波塞利国家公园
they're travelling long distances away from Amboseli -
到更远的地方寻找新的食物和水源
and finding new sources of food and water.
虽然干旱仍在继续
And despite the drought,
但还是有新的幼崽出生
calves are being born.
然而环境变化的节奏太快
But given the pace of change
非洲象面临着严峻的考验
and the challenges they face,
最终能有多少非洲象适应这种变化
how many of Africa's elephants will be able to adapt -
而且适应速度足够快呢
and can they do so fast enough?
辽阔的戈壁沙漠
The Gobi Desert -
这里有无尽的黄沙和皑皑白雪
a land of sand and snow.
至少100万年来
For at least a million years
这里一直是地球上环境最为恶劣的区域之一
this has been one of the most extrme habitats on Earth.
但沙地上的足迹说明
Yet footprints in the sand reveal
这里依然有生命存在
that there is life here.
雪豹总是显得行踪诡秘
A snow leopard, seldom seen,
在这样炎热 干燥的环境中更是难得一见
especially in such hot, arid conditions.
它们的生活区域可以延伸到海拔2000米
They live up to two thousand meters above sea level,
领地范围广阔
and patrol vast territories.
雪豹很少会被发现与同类待在一起
They are rarely seen together.
这是一只雌性雪豹
A mother
和它的幼崽们
with cubs -
这是我们第一次拍摄到
filmed here for the first time
雪豹与幼崽相处的亲密画面
in such intimate detail…
这让我们有机会了解雪豹家族的
and they give us a glimpse of their family life -
生活细节
such as it is.
雪豹幼崽与妈妈一起生活的时间
Snow leopard cubs stay with their mothers
比其它大型猫科动物都要长
longer than those of almost any other big cat.
它们要花费两年多的时间
They remain together for over two years…
向妈妈学习如何应对极端环境带来的挑战
as they learn how to master the extremes.
雪豹凭借杰出的适应性
Which they do so well,
可以生活在地球上最炎热 最寒冷
that they are able to thrive in some of the hottest, coldest,
以及海拔最高的区域
and highest places on Earth.
一些动物经过几百万年的演化
Some animals - over millions of years -
已经学会了很多种极端环境中的生存技巧
have evolved ways of surviving extremely hostile conditions.
但随着“极端”环境的进一步恶化
But as the 'extremes' become more extreme;
它们演化的过程似乎显得有些跟不上节奏了
evolution is being outpaced.
这些异常恶劣的环境
These extraordinary places
如今依然是地球上
are still inhabited by some of Earth's
很多适应力最强的生物的家园
most resilient and adaptable species.
但在快速变化的全球环境中
But in our rapidly changing world,
也许我们未来再无法欣赏到
this is Planet Earth
这样壮美的《地球脉动》
as you may never see it again.
地球上最极端的恶劣环境
The most extreme parts of our planet
有时也会出现在意想不到的地方
are not always found where you might expect.
在越南的丛林深处
Hidden deep in the forests of Vietnam…
当地居民何卿
a local man, Mr Ho Khanh,
发现了一处令人震惊的奇观
made an extraordinary discovery.
有一天下午下雨
One rainy afternoon
我在一个开阔的山洞里躲雨
I sheltered in a cave opening.
我发现突然从洞里升腾起了雾
I saw mist rising from the inside.
它与其它山洞很不一样
It was different from the other caves.
何卿当时并不知道
He didn't know it at the time,
他偶然发现的这处山洞
but he had stumbled upon arguably
可能是全球规模最大的地下洞穴
the largest cave in the world.
我非常骄傲而且很荣幸
It's a source of pride and honour
有机会向世界展示这样宏伟的洞穴
to show the world such a magnificent cave.
《地球脉动》摄制组对这次发现很感兴趣
Inspired by Mr Ho Khanh's discovery,
于是决定到韩松洞进行拍摄
the Planet Earth team set out to film Hang Son Doong…
但首先团队必须到达那里
but first they have to get there.
我们已经离开河谷
We've left the river valley
要逆流而上寻找洞口
and we're walking uphill now to the entrance,
这是一片非常茂密的森林
it's just a thick thick forest.
摄制组在森林中艰难跋涉了两天
After trekking for two gruelling days,
终于找到了这处山洞
the team finally arrive.
下面就是韩松洞的入口
Down here is the entrance to Hang Son Doong.
这个狭小的洞口在密林深处
This tiny opening in this massive jungle.
难以想象居然有人能找到这个地方
It's amazing that anyone ever found this place.
我们要在洞中拍摄18天
We're about to go for the next 18 days,
整个过程都需要照明
and it's lights on from here on out.
当地专家带领摄制组走进了黑暗的洞穴
Local experts guide the team through the darkness.
好的 我可以出发了
Okay. I can go.
我没事 我很好
I'm good, I'm okay.
只是地上很滑
It's just really slippery.
摄制组借助复杂的绳索网络
A complex system of ropes leads them down
完成了90多米的下降
a ninety-metre descent.
小心碰头
Watch your head!
好的 谢谢
Okay, thanks.
在岩石之间攀爬了4个小时之后
After four hours clambering over rocks,
他们终于来到了宿营地点
they finally reach what will be their camp.
摄制组迎来新的一天
The team wake to a new day…
不过周围仍然一片黑暗
but in darkness.
你睡得怎么样 卢克
How did you sleep, Luke?
很累
Quite tired.
后面就是我们温暖的帐篷
These are our lovely tents behind me.
大家可以看到 里面非常舒适
You can see, they're pretty, pretty snug.
我们每天就在这里吃早餐
This is where we have our breakfast every day,
有人负责烹饪
made by some amazing cooks.
这里是我们的充电站
This is our charging station,
有摄影设备的电池
batteries for camera equipment,
照明设备的电池 头灯
batteries for our lights, head torches,
这可是重要的工具
which is so important.
这是我们的水站
This is our water station.
所有这些装备都是靠人力运进来的
Everything that we have got has been brought in by someone,
所以我们不能洗澡 也不能洗漱
so you can't shower or wash.
不只是水
And it's not just water…
总重达到数吨的设备都要靠人力
tonnes of equipment has had to be carried into the cave -
一点一点地搬进山洞
every inch of the way.
摄制组在明亮的灯光下
Now deep underground,
终于体会到了洞穴的巨大和空旷
the powerful lights reveal just how vast this cavern is.
真是不可思议
That is amazing.
太大了
It's huge!
每打开一盏灯
As you turn on each of the lights
就会看到洞内的又一部分空间
another part of this enormous chamber is revealed.
太神奇了 难以置信
It's magic, absolute magic.
为了拍摄出洞内空间的真实效果
To try and capture the true scale,
摄制组打算尝试一种全新的拍摄手法
the team attempt to filming technique never tried before.
我们打算用无人机玩一点花样
We're trying to do a little bit of a dance with the drones
让两架无人机一上一下飞行
whereby we have one drone sort of slightly below the other,
一架负责拍摄
one filming
另一架负责洞内的照明
the other one lighting a feature in the cave…
这里空间狭小
it's a really tight space,
又什么都看不见
you can't see anything,
不知道会出什么差错
what could go wrong.
好 慢一点
OK, slow down a bit.
大家此时都非常紧张
It's making everyone a little nervous.
别再往上了 卢克
Don't go up any higher, Luke.
好 这个高度可以
OK, that's a nice height.
一架无人机负责照明 另一架负责拍摄
With one drone lighting and one drone filming,
于是摄制组发现了
they reveal the wonder
世界上最壮观的石笋奇观
of some of the world's largest stalagmites.
日子一天天过去
As the days pass,
摄制组慢慢适应了地下洞穴里的生活
the team settle into the everyday routine of life underground.
这是一段无缘公共设施的生活
This is the epitome of being off grid.
我们把那个叫作“跷跷板马桶”
We call that one see saw loo,
因为它架在一块岩石上
because it's kind of on a rock
每次坐上去如果往后靠
and every time you sit on it and lean back
都会担心可能发生意外
you're scared that there's going to be a disaster.
最奇特的感受是
The strangest thing is
我们与外界完全失去了联系
having no connection to the outside world whatsoever.
时间仿佛扭曲了
Time is warped,
在地下 一切似乎都失去了意义
nothing makes sense underground.
开灯 开灯
Lights on! Lights on!
没有阳光的指引
Without daylight to guide them,
摄制组没日没夜地工作
the team work round the clock
努力捕捉洞内独特的景色
to capture the cave's most unique features.
其中最为特别的一处景致
Most special of all,
在每年只出现几周时间
an event which happens only a few weeks a year.
要想到达目的地
To get there
摄制组必须穿过布满怪石的通道
they must navigate through boulder fields
和狭窄的地缝
and tight squeezes.
此处的洞穴顶部
Here, around half a million years ago,
大概在50万年前发生过坍塌
the cave roof collapsed,
打开了一扇通往外界的窗口
opening a window to the outside world.
摄制组耐心等待适当的时机
The team wait for just the right conditions.
我们已经在这里待了好几个小时
We've been sat here for hours
最后在右手边的洞壁上
and finally just on the right-hand side of the wall
我们终于看到了一线阳光
you can see the first signs of light.
在黑暗中生活了几周之后
After weeks of darkness,
他们在200多米深的地下
two-hundred metres underground,
见到了照到洞穴地面上的阳光
they see sunlight illuminate the cave floor.
阳光照亮了巨大的洞穴
The way it just lights up this massive cave.
我们之前打开了四五盏灯
When we've been trying to do it with about four or five lights
但只能照亮一小块地方
and barely even lighting the smallest section,
可阳光照进来的时候
when the sun comes in
周围一下子就亮了
it just phorrrr.
我想大家肯定都起了鸡皮疙瘩
I think everyone's got goosebumps.
我以前从来没有像现在这样崇拜阳光
I don't think I've ever appreciated sun so much in my life.
太不可思议了
It's incredible.
快看阳光中的这条瀑布
Look at the backlit waterfalls,
水滴飘落而下
so slow coming down.
这是我平生见过最美的景色
Literally one of the best things I've ever seen.
对摄制组而言
For the crew,
阳光的出现意味着他们的洞穴生活就要结束了
the sunbeam marks a profound end to their time in the cave.
我们出来了
We're outside!
到处绿意盎然 阳光明媚
It's so green, it's so bright.
终于回到地面上了
Being back above ground
感觉像是回家了
feels like where we belong.
令人不禁赞叹的是
It's a wonder to imagine
我们神奇地球的地下
what other extremes still lie
还会隐藏着怎样的极端之境
beneath the surface of Planet Earth.